<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tech on Alessandro Mencarini</title>
    <link>https://amencarini.com/tech/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tech on Alessandro Mencarini</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-UK</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 12:25:59 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://amencarini.com/tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Compelling job specs</title>
      <link>https://amencarini.com/tech/compelling-job-specs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 12:25:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amencarini.com/tech/compelling-job-specs/</guid>
      <description>The quest for the Holy Grail A job spec that developers relate to is a rare sight.
I was chatting with an acquaintance that works in the recruiting space, about the never-ending battle between good an evil that is the relationship between recruiters and developers. The conversation got interesting when he said this:
 I am not sure our job specs are very good.
 At that point, I had a fleeting recollection that while on Twitter, I stumbled on the Zapier jobs page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>React on Phoenix</title>
      <link>https://amencarini.com/tech/react-on-phoenix/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 19:45:29 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amencarini.com/tech/react-on-phoenix/</guid>
      <description>Phoenix&amp;rsquo;s author Chris McCord decided that instead of implementing a brand new pipeline for JavaScript and CSS, it was wiser to rely on existing tools. Specifically, Brunch was chosen.
An advantage of this is that using React with ES6 and JSX is dead easy, as Babel is already available for us.
 In your Phoenix project&amp;rsquo;s directory install the Node modules you&amp;rsquo;ll need:  $ npm install --save react react-dom babel-preset-react   Change brunch-config.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recruiters vs Devs: The Eternal Struggle</title>
      <link>https://amencarini.com/tech/recruiters-vs-devs-the-eternal-struggle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 10:05:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amencarini.com/tech/recruiters-vs-devs-the-eternal-struggle/</guid>
      <description>A sour relationship The relationship between developers and recruiters is not an easy one.
For developers, recruiters are mostly a pain in the back, bothering them at all times of the day in order to offer jobs completely irrelevant to any goal a developer has in their career.
For recruiters, developers end up being a bunch of spoiled kids who whine about job postings and bash recruiters (privately and publicly) because it builds camaraderie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out Elm</title>
      <link>https://amencarini.com/tech/trying-out-elm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 13:56:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amencarini.com/tech/trying-out-elm/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been out of the front-end game for a while, and decided to dip my toes back again after roughly 2 years of little-to-none JavaScript. So many things happened in the meanwhile! React, Redux, Flux, Om&amp;hellip; What should I use to get back on track?
As I&amp;rsquo;ve been dabbling a lot in Elixir and Phoenix space, I saw in the community a growing interest for Elm, a functional language that compiles to JavaScript.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>